[Music]
This is software engineering radio the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the e computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[Music]
Hey, this is Jeremy Jung for Software Engineering Radio and today I'm talking to Francois Dowst.
He's a staff member at the W3C.
And we're going to talk about the W3C.
and the recommendation process and discuss Francois's experience with how these features end up in our browsers.
So, Franuis, welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you, Jeremy, and many thanks for the invitation.
I'm really thrilled to be part of this podcast.
I think many of our listeners will have heard about the W3C,
but they may not actually know what it is. So, could you start by explaining what it is?
Sure.
So, W3C stands for the Worldwide Web Consortium.
It's a standardization organization.
I guess that's how people should think about W3C.
It was created in 1994 by Tim Bernersley who is the inventor of the web.
Tim Bernersley was the director of W3C for a long long time.
He retired not long ago few years back and the B3C has a number of uh properties.
Let's say first the goal is to produce royalty-free standards and that's very important.
We want to make sure that the standard.
that get produced can be used and implemented without having to pay fees to anyone.
We do web standards.
I didn't mention it but it's from the name standards.
that you find in your web browsers but not only that.
there are number of other standards that got W3C including for example XML data related standards.
W3C as an organization is a consortium the the C stands for consortium legally speaking it's a it's.
a 501c3 meaning in.
so it's a US-based legal entity not for profit.
and the the little free is important because it means it's public interest.
That means we are a consortium.
That means we have members, but at the same time, the goal, the mission is to the public.
So, we're not only just doing what our members want,
we're also making sure that what our members want is aligned with what end users in the end. need.
And the BreeC has a small team.
And so, I'm part of this team worldwide, 45 to 55 people depending on how you count.
mostly technical people and some admin as well overseeing the work that we do at W3C.
And so you mentioned there's 45 to 55 people. How is this funded?
Is this from governments or commercial companies?
The main source comes from membership fees.
So the B3C has uh so members uh roughly 350 members at W3C.
and in order to become a member an organization needs to pay an annual membership fee.
That's pretty common among standardization organizations and we only have I guess three levels of membership fees.
Well you may find additional small levels but three main ones.
The goal is to make sure that a big player will not a big player.
or large company will not have more rights than anything anyone else.
but we try to make sure that all members have equal rights is not perfect.
but that's how things are set.
So that's the main source of income for the B3C.
and then we try to diversify just a little bit to get uh for example we go to.
governments we may go to governments in the EU.
EU we may uh take some uh grant for EU research projects.
that allow us you know to study explore topics.
uh in the US there there used to be some funding from coming from the government as.
well that's also a source. but the main one is membership.
and you mentioned that a lot of the W3C's work is related to web standards.
There's other groups like TC39 which works on the JavaScript spec.
and the IATF which I believe worked with your group on WebRTC.
I wonder if you could explain W3C's connection to other groups like that.
Sure.
We try to collaborate with a number of other standardization organizations.
So in general everything goes well because you you have a clear separation of concerns.
So you mentioned TC39 indeed they they are the ones.
who standardize JavaScript proper name of JavaScript is ECMAScript.
So that's DC TC39 the technical committee at ECMA.
and so we have indeed interactions with them.
because their work directly impact the JavaScript that you're going to run in your in your web browser.
and we develop a number of JavaScript APIs actually in W3C.
So we need to make sure that the way we develop these APIs align with the the language. itself.
With ITF the the boundary is clear as well.
It's a protocol for network protocols for the ITF an application level for uh W3C.
That's usually how the distinction is made.
The boundaries are always a bit fuzzy.
but that's how things work and usually uh things work pretty well.
There's also the wet wiggi and the wet wuge is more the the history was more complicated.
because uh the wet wuge was created out of a fork of the HTML specification at the time.
when it was developed by W3C a long time ago.
and there was been some uh disagreement on the way things should have been done.
and the wet widget took over got created took this the HTML spec.
and did it a different way went in another direction.
and that other direction actually ended up being the direction.
So that's a success uh from there.
and so W4C no longer works no longer owns the uh HTML spec.
and the WEBG has taken taken up a number of uh of different core specifications for the web.
doing a lot of work on interoperability.
and making sure that the algorithms specified by the spec were correct.
which which was something that historically we haven't been very good at at W3C.
and the way they've been working as uh has a lot of influence on the way we develop.
now the APIs from a W3C perspective.
So just to make sure I understand correctly,
you have TC39 which is focused on the JavaScript or ECMAScript language itself.
and you have APIs that are going to use JavaScript and interact with JavaScript.
So you need to coordinate there.
The WHWG they have the specification for HTML. than the IATF.
They are I'm not sure if the.
right term would be they would be one level lower perhaps than the W3C.
That's how you you can formulate it.
Yes.
A one layer one in the ISO network in the ISO stack the the network level.
And so in that case, one place I've heard it mentioned is that WebRTC to use it,
there is an IETF specification and then perhaps there's a W3C recommendation and-
yes, so when we created the web RTC working group that was in 2011,
I think it was created with a dual head.
There was one RTC web group that got created at IETF.
and a web RTC group that got created at W3C.
And that was done on purpose.
Of course, the goal was not to compete on the on the solution, but.
actually to have the two sides of the uh solution be developed in parallel,
the application front and the network front.
And there's still a lot of overlap in participation between both groups.
And that's what keep things successful in the end.
It's not, you know, process or organization to organization relationships coordination at the organization level.
It's really the fact that you have participants.
that are essentially the same on both sides of the equation that helps move things forward.
Now, WebRTC is a is more complex than just one group at ITF.
Web RTC is a very complex set of technology, stack of technologies.
So when you pull a little protocol from ITF suddenly you have the whole ITF.
that comes with you with it.
So you you have the feeling that WebRTC needs all of the uh internet protocols. that got created to work.
and I think probably a lot of web developers they may hear words like specification.
or standard but I believe the official term at least at the W3C is this recommendation.
And so I wonder if you can explain what that means.
It means standard in the end.
And that came from initially that comes from a time.
where as many standardization organizations W3C was created not to be a standardization organization.
It was felt that standard was not the right term because we were not a standardization organization.
So recommend IETF has the same thing.
They call it RFC request for comment which stands for nothing in and yet it's a standard.
So WC was created with the same kind of a thing.
We needed some other terminology and we call that recommendation.
But in the end that's standard.
It's really how you should see it.
And one thing I didn't mention when I introduced W3C is there are two types of standards in. the end.
Two main categories.
There are the jury standards and de facto standards to families.
The jury standards are the ones that are imposed by some kind of regulation.
So it's usually a standard you see imposed by governments for example.
So when you look at your electric plug at home,
there's some regulation there that says this plug needs to have these properties.
and that's a standard that gets imposed.
It's a danger jury standard.
And then there are de facto standards.
which are really uh specifications that are out there and people agree to use it to implement it.
and by virtue of being used and implemented and used by everyone they become standards.
The WC really is in the second part.
It's a de facto standard. IETF is the same thing.
Some of our standards are used in are referenced in regulations now.
but just a minority of them most of them are de facto standards.
and that's important because that's in the end it doesn't matter what the specification says even.
though it's a bit confusing.
what matters is that the what the specification says matches what implementations actually implement.
and that these implementations are used and are used interoperably across browsers for example.
or across implementations across users.
cross usages.
So standardization is a lengthy process.
The recommendation is the final stage in that lengthy process.
More and more we don't really reach recommendation anymore. If you look at uh at groups.
because we have another path let's say we can stop at candidate recommendation.
which is in theoretically a step before that.
but then you you can stay there and stay there forever and publish new candidate recommendations later on.
What matters again is that you get this virtuous feedback loop with implementers and usage.
So if the candidate recommendation ends up being implemented by all the browsers,
what's ends up being the distinction between a candidate and one that's a normal recommendation?
So today it's mostly a process thing.
Some groups actually decide to go to rack, some groups decide to stay at candidate rack.
and there's no formal difference between the the two.
We've adjusted the process so that the important bits.
that applied at the recommendation level now apply at the candidate rec level.
And by important things I mean the patent commitments.
Typically the patent policy fully applies at the candidate recommendation level.
so that you get your protection the royalty-free protection that we are aiming at.
Some people do not care, you know,
but most of the world still works with uh with patents for good or bad reasons, but that's how things work.
So, we're trying to make sure that we we secure the.
right set of um of patent commitments from the right set of stakeholders.
Oh, so when someone implements a W3C recommendation or a candidate recommendation,
the patent holders related to that recommendation, they basically agree to allow royalty-free use of that patent.
They do.
the one that were involved in the working group.
Of course, I mean, we can't say anything about the companies out there.
that may have patents and we're not part of this standardization process.
There's always it's a remaining risk, but part of the goal.
when we create a working group is to make sure that people understand the scope.
lawyers look into it and the the legal teams.
that exist at the all the large companies basically gave a green light.
saying yeah we're pretty confident that we know.
where the patents are on this particular area.
and we're fine also letting go of the the patents we own ourselves.
and I think you had mentioned what ends up being the most important is.
that the browser creators implement these recommendations.
So it sounds like maybe the distinction between candidate recommendation.
and recommendation almost doesn't matter as long as you get the end result you want.
People will have different opinions in the in standardization circles.
and I mentioned also WC is working on other kind of standards.
So in some other areas the nuance may be more important.
but when you look at specifications that target web browsers we've switched from a model where.
specs were developed first and then implemented to a model.
where specs and implementations are being worked in parallel.
This actually relates to the evolution I was mentioning with the wet widget taking over the HTML.
and focusing on the interoperability issues.
because the starting point was yeah we have an HTML 4.01 01 spec.
but it's not interoperable because it's not specified.
There are number of areas that are gray areas you can implement them differently.
and so there are interoperable issues.
Back to candidate break actually the stage was created.
if I remember correctly if I'm if I'm not wrong.
the stage was created following the uh IE6 problem in the CSS working group.
IE6 shipped with some version of CSS that was in the as specified.
The spec was saying, you know, do.
that for the CSS box model and the I6 was following that.
And then the group decided to change the box model and suddenly I6 was no longer compliant and.
that created a a huge mess on the in the history of of the web in a way.
And so the the candidate recommendation stage was introduced following.
that to try to catch these kind of problems.
But nowadays again we we switch to another model where it's more live.
and so we you'll find a number of specs that are not even at candidate correct level.
They are at the what we call a working draft and they are being implemented.
and if all goes well the standardization process follows the implementation.
and then you end up in a situation where you have your candidate wreck when the spec ships.
A recent example would be a web GPU for example.
It has shipped in uh in Chrome shortly before it transitioned to Candidatrack,
but the spec was already stable.
and now it's shipping uh in in different browsers, Safari and Firefox.
That's a good example of something that follows things along pretty well.
But then you have other specs such as uh in the media space,
request video frame call back is a short API.
that allows you to get a call back whenever the the browser renders a video frame essentially.
And that spec is implemented across browsers.
But from a W3C specific perspective, it does not even exist.
It's not on the standardization track.
It's still being incubated in what we call a community group,
which is something that usually exists before we move to the the standardization process.
There are examples of things where something fell through the cracks.
or the standardization process is either too early or too late.
things that are in spec are not exactly what what got implemented.
or implementations are too early in the process.
We're doing a better job at not falling into a trap.
where someone ships an implementation and then suddenly everything is frozen.
You can no longer change it because it's too late it shipped.
We've tried different paths there and mentioned CSS.
there was this kind of vendor prefixed properties.
that used to be uh the way uh browsers were deploying new features without taking the final name.
We're trying also to move away from it because same thing then.
in the end you end up with applications.
that have duplicate all the property the CSS properties in the stylesheets with the vendor prefixes.
and nuances in the in what it does in the end.
Yeah, I think is that in CSS where you'll see d-mosilla or things like that.
The example of the request video frame call back.
I wonder if you have an opinion.
or or or know why that ended up the way it did.
where the browsers all implemented it even though it was still in the incubation stage.
on this one.
I don't have a particular uh insights on whether there was,
you know, a strong reason to implement it without doing the standardization work.
I mean, there it's not an IPR issue.
It's not something that I don't think the the the spec triggers problems.
that would be controversial or whatever.
So it's just a matter of uh that was no one's priority.
and in the end you end up with a everyone's happy it has shipped and so now.
doing the spec work is a bit why spend time on something that's already shipped and so on.
but it may still come back at some point we'll try to you know improve the situation.
Yeah that's that's interesting.
It's a little counterintuitive because it sounds like you have the the working group.
and it sounds like perhaps the companies or organizations involved, they maybe agreed on how it should work.
and maybe that agreement almost made it so that they felt like.
they didn't need to move forward with the specification.
because they came to consensus even before going through that.
In this particular case, it's probably because it's really again it's a small spec. It's just one function call.
I mean they will definitely want a working group for larger specifications.
By the way, actually now I know request video frame call back.
It's because they the final goal now.
that it's shipped is to merge it into HTML the HTML spec.
So there's a there's an ongoing issue on the the wet wuge side to integrate request video frame. call back.
and it's taking some time but see it caught up.
and uh someone is doing the the work to do it. I had forgotten about this one.
So with larger specifications organizations will want this kind of IPR regime.
They will want commitments from uh others on the scope on the process on everything.
So, they will want a more formal setting.
because that's part of how you ensure that things will get done properly.
I didn't mention it, but something we're really uh pushy on at W3C.
I mentioned we have principles, we have priorities, and we have several uh properties at W3C.
And one of them is that we're very strong on horizontal reviews of our specs.
We really want them to be reviewed from an accessibility perspective,
from an internationalization perspective, from a privacy and security perspective and a technical architecture perspective as well.
And these reviews are part of the formal process.
So you all specs need to undergo these reviews and from time to time that creates tension.
From time to time it just goes without problem.
A recurring issue is that privacy and security are hard.
I mean it's not an easy problem.
something that can be solved easily.
So there's an ongoing tension and no easy way to resolve it,
but there's an ongoing tension between specifying powerful APIs and preserving privacy.
meaning not exposing too much information to applications.
In the media space, you can think of the media capabilities API.
So the media space is a complicated space because of codecs.
Codexs are typically not relative free and so browsers decide which codecs they're going to support,
which audio and video codecs they they're going to support.
And doing that that creates additional fragmentation, not in the sense that they're not interoperable, but.
in the sense that applications need to choose.
which codec they're going to ship the stream to the end user.
And uh it's all the more complicated that some codecs are going to be hardware supported.
So you will have a hardware decoder in your laptop.
or smartphone and so that's going to be efficient to decode some stream.
whereas some codecs are are going to be softwarebased supported and that may consume a lot of CPU.
and a lot of power and a lot of energy in the end.
So you you'll want to avoid that if you can select another thing.
And it's even more complex than codecs have different profiles,
lower end profiles, higher end profiles with different capabilities, different features.
depending on whether you're going to use this or that color space,
for example, this or that resolution, whatever.
And so you want to suffice that to web applications.
because otherwise they can't select they can't choose the right codec.
and the right stream that they're going to send to the uh client devices.
and so they're not going to provide an efficient user experience first.
and even a sustainable one in terms of energy.
because they're they're going to waste energy if they don't send the right stream.
So you want to suffice that to application that's what the media capabilities API provides.
But at the same time, if you expose that information,
you end up with ways to fingerprint the end user's device.
that in turn is often used to track users across sites,
which is exactly what we don't want to have for privacy reasons, for obvious privacy reasons.
So, you have to balance that and find ways to expose capabilities without necessarily exposing them too much.
Yeah.
Can you give an example of how some of those discussions went like within the working group?
Who are the companies or who are the organizations.
that are arguing for we shouldn't have this capability because of the privacy concerns-
or in a way all of the companies have a vision of uh of privacy.
I mean they you will have a hard time finding members saying I don't care about privacy.
I just want the feature.
Uh they all have privacy in mind but they may have a different approach to privacy.
So if you take uh want to say Apple.
and Google would be the the I guess the perfect examples in that in that space.
Google will have a an approach that is more open-ended saying the the user agents should check what.
the given site is doing.
and then if it goes beyond some kind of threshold they're going to say well okay well.
we stop exposing data to that site to that application so monitor and react in a way.
Apple has a more you know has a stricter view on on privacy let's say.
and they will say no the feature must not exist in the first place or.
but that's I mean I guess some it's not always.
that extreme and uh from time to time it's the opposite.
You will have you know Apple arguing in one way.
which is more open-ended than the than Google for example and they are not the only ones.
So in working groups you will find usually the implementers.
So when we talk about APIs that get implemented in browsers you.
want the core browsers to be involved.
otherwise it's usually not a good sign for the success of the uh of the technology.
So in practice that means Apple, Microsoft, Modia.
Which one did I forget? Google.
Google. I forgot Google of course.
Thank you.
That's the core list of participants you want to have in any uh group.
that develops web standards targeted at web browsers.
And then on top of that, you want organizations.
and people who are directly going to use it either because they well the content providers.
So in in media for example if you look at the media working group you will see uh. so.
browser vendors the ones I mentioned content providers such as the BBC Netflix chipset vendors would would be. there as well Intel Nvidia.
again because there's a hardware decoding in there.
and encoding so media is touches on on hardware device manufacturer in general.
you may I think Sony is involved in the in the media working group for example.
and these companies are usually less active in the spec development it depends on the groups.
but They're usually less active because the ones developing the specs are usually the browser again.
because as I mentioned we develop the specs in parallel to browsers implementing it.
So they have the the feedback on how to formulate the the algorithms.
and so that's this collection of people who are going to discuss first within themselves.
WC pushes for consensual decisions.
So we hardly take any votes in working groups.
but from then time that's not enough.
and there may be disagreements but let's say there's agreement in the group.
when the spec matures horizontal review groups will look at the spec.
So these are groups I mentioned accessibility one uh privacy internationalization.
and these groups usually the participants are it depends it can be anything it can be uh the.
same companies it can be but usually.
different people from the same companies.
but they they may be organizations with that come from very a very different angle and.
that's a good thing because that means the you know you enlarge the the perspectives on the on. the technology.
that's when you have a discussion between groups.
that takes case and from time to time it goes well.
From time to time again it can trigger issues that are hard to solve.
and the BC has an escalation process in case in case things generate.
starting with the notion of formal objection.
It makes sense that you would have the the browser vendors.
and you have all the different companies that.
would use that browser, all the different horizontal groups like you mentioned the internationalization and accessibility.
I would imagine that you were talking about consensus.
and there are certain groups or certain companies that maybe have more say or more sway.
For example, if you're a browser manufacturer, you're Google.
I'm kind of curious how that works out within the working group.
Yes, it's I guess I would be lying.
if I were saying that all companies are strictly equal in a in a in a group.
They are from a process perspective.
I mentioned the different membership fees, but were designed spec specifically.
so so that no one could say I'm putting in a lot of money,
so you you need to respect me.
and you need to follow what I what I want to what I want to do.
At the same time, if you take a company like like Google for.
example, they send hundreds of engineers to do standardization work,
that's absolutely fantastic because that means work progresses and it's a extremely smart people.
So that's really a pleasure to work with these people.
But you need to take a step back and say well the problem is the facto that.
give them more power just by virtue of uh injecting more resources into it.
So having always someone who can respond to an issue,
having always someone editing a spec, the facto that.
give them more uh more say on the directions that get forward.
and on top of that of course they have the it's not surprisingly the the browser.
that is used the most currently on the market.
We try very hard to make sure that things are balanced.
It's not a perfect world. the role of the team. I mean, I didn't talk about the role of the team,
but part of it is to make sure that.
again all perspectives are represented and that there's not such a big imbalance that something is wrong.
and that we really need to look into it.
So, making sure that anyone if they have something to say,
making sure that they are heard by the rest of the group.
and not dismissed that usually goes well.
There's no problem with that.
And again the escalation process I mentioned it doesn't make any difference between a small player a large. player a big player.
we have small companies raising formal objections against some of our specs.
that happens or large ones but that happens too.
there's no magical solution I guess you can tell it by the way I uh I don't know.
how to formulate the the process more it's a human process.
and that's very important that it remains a human process as well.
and I suppose the role of staff.
and someone in your position for example is to try and ensure that these different groups are heard.
and it isn't just one group taking control of it.
That's part of the role again is to make sure that the process is followed.
So the I don't want to give the impression that the process controls everything in the group.
The groups are bound by the process but the process is there to catch problems when they arise.
Most of the time there are no problems.
It's just again participants talking to each other, talking with the rest of the community.
Most of the work happens in public nowadays in any case.
So the groups work in public essentially through asynchronous discussions on GitHub repositories.
There are contributions from non group participants and everything goes well and so the process doesn't kick in.
You just never say, Hey, no, you didn't respect the process there. You you closed the issue.
You shouldn't have that.
It's pretty rare that you have to do that.
things just proceed naturally because they all everyone understands where they are,
why what they're doing and why they're doing it.
We still have a role I guess in in the sense.
that from time to time that doesn't work and you have to intervene.
and you have to make sure that the exception is code.
and uh and processed in the right way.
And you said this process is asynchronous and public.
So is this in GitHub issues or how how would somebody go. and and see what the results of-
Yes, there there are basically a gazillion of GitHub repositories under the uh W3C organization on GitHub.
Most groups are using GitHub.
I mean there's no it's not mandatory.
We don't mandate any uh any tooling.
but the fact is that most we've been transitioning to GitHub for a number of years already.
So that's where the work most of the work happens through issues through pull requests.
That's where people can go and raise issues against specifications.
We usually uh also some from time to time get feedback from developers encountering a bug in a.
particular implementations.
which we try to gently redirect to uh the actual bug trackers.
because we're not responsible for the implementations of the specs unless the spec is not clear.
We are responsible for the spec itself.
and making sure that the spec is clear and that implementers understand how they should implement something.
I can see how people would make that mistake because they they see it's the feature.
but that's not the responsibility of the the W3C to implement any of the specifications.
something you had mentioned there's the issue of intellectual property rights and how when you.
have a recommendation you require the different organizations involved to make their patents available to use freely.
I wonder why there was never any kind of recommendation for audio or video codecs in browsers.
since you have certain ones that are considered royalty-free.
But I believe that's never been specified at W3C. I mean, yes, we've tried.
I mean, it's not for lack of trying.
We've had a number of discussions with various stakeholders saying,
Hey, we we really need an audio or video codec for for the web.
The PNG ping is an example of an image format which got standardized at W3C.
and it got standardized at W3C for similar reasons.
there had to be a royalty-free image format for the web.
and there was known at the time of course nowadays JPEG.
and GIF or GIF whatever you call it are no problem with them.
but but at the time ping was really meant to address this issue and it worked for ping.
for audio and video we haven't managed to secure commitments by stakeholders so willingness to do it.
so it's not it's not lack of willingness we would have loved to get a royalty-free free uh.
audio codec or royalty-free video codec.
Again, audio and video codecs are extremely complicated because of this not only because of patterns.
but also because of the entire business ecosystem that exists around them for good reasons.
In order for a a codec to be supported, deployed, effective, it needs to mature a lot.
It needs to be added to at a hardware level to a number of devices capturing devices.
but also u of course players.
and that takes a lot of time.
and that's where you also enter a number of business considerations with business contracts between entities.
So on a personal level, I'm I'm pleased to see for example the Alliance for Open Media working.
on AV1, which is at least they want it to be royalty-free.
and they've been adopting actually the W3C patent policy to do this work.
So we're pleased to see that been adopting the same process and same thing.
AV1 is not yet at the same support stage as other codecs in the world. Yeah. In devices.
as an open question as what are we going to do in the future uh with that.
it's doubtful that the 4C will be able to work on a royalty-free audio codec.
or royalty-free video codec itself because probably it's too late now in any case.
but it it's one of these angles in the in the web platform.
where we wish we had a technology available for for free.
and uh it's not exactly uh how things work in practice.
I mean the way Codex are developed remains really patentoriented and you will find more codecs being developed.
and that's where geopolitics can even enter the play.
because uh if you go to China you will find new codecs emerging that get developed within China.
also because the other codex come mostly from the US so it's a bit of a problem.
and so I'm not going to enter details.
and uh I would probably say a stupid things in any case.
so we continue to see uh emerging codex.
that are not reality free and it's probably going to remain the case for a number of years.
Unfortunately, unfortunately from a W3C perspective and from my perspective,
of course, there's always these new formats coming out.
and the rate at which they get supported in the browser even on a per browser basis is.
very there can be a long time.
between for example WEBP being released and a browser supporting it.
So, seems like maybe we're going to be in.
that situation for a while where the codecs will come out.
and maybe the browsers will support them, maybe they won't, but the timeline is very uncertain.
Something you had mentioned, maybe this was in your email to me earlier, but you had mentioned that.
some of these specifications there's there's business considerations like with digital rights management and media source extensions.
I wonder if you could talk a little bit about maybe what media source extensions is.
and encrypted media extensions and and what the considerations or challenges are there.
Well, I'm going to go very very quickly over the history of video.
and audio support on the web.
Initially, it was supported through plugins.
You're maybe too young to remember that,
but we had extensions added to real player these kind of things.
Flash as well supporting uh videos in web pages.
but it was not provided by the web browsers themselves.
Then HTML 5 changed the situation adding these new tags audio and video.
but these tags only by default support you give them a resource like an image.
that it's an audio.
or a video file they're going to download this video file.
or audio file and they're going to play it.
that works well.
But as soon as you want to do any kind of real streaming,
the files are too large to stream to to get,
you know, to get just a single fetch on them.
So you really want to stream them chunk by chunk.
and you want to adapt the resolution at which you send the stream based on realtime conditions,
the user's network.
If there's plenty of bandwidth, you want to send the user the highest possible resolution.
If there's some kind of hiccup, temporary hiccup in the the network,
you really want to lower the resolution and that's called adaptive streaming.
And to get adaptive streaming on the web, well, there are a number of protocols that exist.
Same thing.
Some many of them are proprietary and actually they remain proprietary to some extent.
and some of them are over HTTP.
and there are the ones that are primarily used in web contexts.
So, Dash comes to mind, dash for dynamic adaptive streaming over HTTP.
HLS is another one initially developed by Apple I believe and it's uh HTTP live streaming probably exactly.
and so there are different protocols that you can use.
so the goal was not to standardize these protocols because again there were some proprietary aspects to them.
and same thing as with Codex there was no.
well at least people wanted to have the uh flexibility to tweak parameters adaptive streaming parameters the way. they wanted.
or different scenarios you may want to tweak the parameters differently.
so There needed to be more flexibility on top of protocols not being truly available for use directly.
and for implementation directly in browsers.
It was also about providing applications with the flexibility they would need to tweak parameters.
So media source extensions comes into play for exactly that.
Media source extensions is really about you.
The application fetches chunks of its audio.
and video stream the way it wants.
and with the parameters it wants and it adjusts whatever it wants.
and then it feed that into the uh video.
or audio tag and the browser takes care of the rest.
So it's really about doing you know the adaptive streaming let applications do it.
and then let the user agent the browser take care of the rendering itself.
That's media source extensions.
Initially it was pushed by Netflix.
They were not the only ones of course.
but that there was a major proponent of this uh technical solution.
because they were expanding all over the world with plenty of native applications on all sorts of devices.
and they wanted to have a way to stream content on the web as well.
both I guess to expand to a new ecosystem the web providing new opportunities let's say.
but at the same time also to have a fall back because for.
native support on different platforms they sometimes had to enter business agreements with the hardware manufacturers,
the service provider or whatever.
and so that was a way to have a fall back.
that kind of work is more open in case things take some time.
and so so they probably had other reasons.
I mean I'm I can't speak on behalf of Netflix on others.
but they were not the only ones of course supporting this media source extension specification.
and that went kind of well I think it was created in 2011.
I mean the the work started in 2011.
and the recommendation was published in 2016 which is not too bad from a standardization perspective.
it means only 5 years you know it's a very short amount of time at the same time.
and in parallel and complement to the media source extension specifications.
There was work on the encrypted media extensions.
and here it was pushed by the same proponents in a way.
because they wanted to get premium content on the web.
and by premium content you think of movies and these kind of beasts.
and the problem with the I guess the basic issue with digital assets as movies is.
that they cost hundreds of millions to produce. I mean some cost less of course.
and yet it's super easy to copy them if you have access to the digital uh file.
You just copy and that's it.
Paracy is super easy to achieve.
It's illegal of course but it's super easy to do.
And so that's where the different legislations come into play with digital right management.
Then the fact is most countries allow system.
that can encrypt content and through what we call DRM systems.
So content providers, the ones that have movies.
or the studios here and Netflix is one of one of the studios nowadays.
But not only not only them, all major studios will uh would push for wanted to have something. that.
would allow them to stream encrypted content, encrypted audio and video, mostly video to web applications.
so that they could provide the movies.
Otherwise they basically saying and sorry but this premium content will never make it to the web.
because there's no way we're going to send it in clear to the end user.
So encrypted media extensions is an API.
that allows to interface with what's called the content decryption module CDM.
which itself interacts with the DRM systems that the browser may may or may not support.
And so it provides a way for an application to receive encrypted content,
pass it over, get the the right keys, the right license keys from whatever system.
actually pass that logic over to the and to the user agent,
which passes it over to the CDM system,
which is kind of a black box that does its magic to get the right decryption key.
and then the and to decrypt the content that can be rendered.
The encrypted media extensions triggered a lot of uh controversy because it's DRM and DRM systems.
Many people uh think should be banned especially on the web.
because the premise of the web is that the the user trusts a user agent.
The the web browser is called a user agent in all of our specifications.
and that's the trust relationship.
and then they interact with a a content provider.
and so whatever they do with the content is their essentially their problem.
and DRM introduces a third party which is the end user no longer has the control on the.
content it has to rely on something.
else that restricts what it can achieve with the content.
so it's it's not only a trust relationship with its user agents it's also with with something else.
which is the content provider in the end the one.
that has the the license where provides the license.
and so that's that triggers a hell of a lot of of discussions in the B3C degenerated into.
formal objections being raised again the specification.
that escalated to the I mean at all leverage.
it's the the story in W3C that really uh divided the membership into oppos if you.
that's not was not on the year it was not really 50/50 in the sense not just a. huge fight.
but the that triggered a lot of discussions and a lot of of formal objections at the time.
we were still from a governance perspective interestingly um the BC used to be a dictatorship it's not.
how you should formulate it.
of course but it was a benevolent dictatorship you could see it this way.
in the sense that the whole process escalated to one single person was Tim Berners Lee.
who had the final say.
when none of the other layers had managed to catch and to resolve a conflict.
and that has hardly ever happened in the history of W3C.
but that happened to W to for EM for encrypted media extensions it had to go to the.
director level.
who after due consideration decided to allow the EM to proceed that's why we have an EM standard. right now.
but still it remains something on the side EM we're still uh it's still in scope of the.
media working group for example.
but the scope if you look at the charter of the working group we try to scope the.
updates we can make to the specification.
to make sure that we don't reopen a kind of worms.
because well it's really a a topic that triggers friction for good and bad reasons.
and when you talk about the media source extensions.
that is the ability to write custom code to stream video in whatever way.
you want you mentioned the meg dash and http live streaming.
So in that case would that be the developer gets to write.
that code in JavaScript that's executed by the browser?
Yeah, that would be it.
And then typically I guess the approach nowadays is more.
and more to develop low-level APIs in B3C or web in general I guess.
and to let uh libraries emerge that are going to make life of a developer easier. So for me dash you have dash.js.
which does a fantastic job at implementing the complexity of of adaptive streaming.
and you just you just hook it into your your workflow and that's it.
And with the encrypted media extensions I'm trying to picture how those work and how they work differently.
Well, it's because the key architecture is that the the stream that you the stream that.
you may assemble with media source extensions, for example, because typically they they used in collaboration.
When you hook it into the video tag,
you also call EM and actually the stream goes to EM.
And when it goes to EM, actually the user agent hands the encrypted stream.
You're still encrypted at this time.
encrypted uh stream goes to the CDM content decryption module and that's a black box.
Well, it has some blackbox logic. So, it's not uh even if you look at the chromium source code,
for example, you won't see the implementation of the CDM because it's a it's a black box.
It's not part of the browser, it's a it's sandboxed.
Its execution is sandboxed.
That's the EM is kind of unique in in this way.
where the the CDM is not allowed to make network requests, for example, again for privacy reasons.
So anyway, the this CDM box has the logic to decrypt the content and it hands it over.
and then it depends it depends on the level of protection you you need. or that the system supports.
It can be against softwarebased protection in.
which case actually a highly motivated attacker could uh actually get access to the decoded stream.
or it can be more hardware protected in.
which case actually the it goes to the uh your final screen but.
it goes it goes through the hardware in a in a mode.
that the OS supports in a mode that even the user agent doesn't have access to it.
So it doesn't it can't even see the pixels that gets rendered on the screen.
There are several other uh APIs that you could use for example to take a screenshot of your. your application and so on.
and you cannot apply them to such content.
because they're just going to return a black box again.
because the user agent itself does not see the pixels.
which is exactly what you want with encrypted content.
and the the content decryption module it's if I understand correctly it's something that's shipped with the browsers.
but you were saying is if you were to look at the public source code of Chromium.
or of Firefox, you would not see that implementation.
True.
The typical examples are uh White Vine. So, White Vine.
So, interestingly speaking, in theory, these uh systems could have been provided by anyone.
In practice, they've been provided by the browser vendors themselves.
So, Google has White Vine, Microsoft has something called Play Ready, Apple, the name escapes my mind.
So, they that's basically what they support.
So they they also own that code but in a way they don't have to.
and Firefox actually uh they I don't remember.
which one they support among these three.
but they don't own that code typically they provide a wrapper around around it.
Yeah, that's that's exactly the the crux of the uh issue that people have with uh with DRM,
right?
It's uh the fact that uh suddenly you have a bit of code running there.
that is uh that.
okay, you can send box, but you cannot inspect and you don't have access to its source code.
Yeah, that's interesting.
So the almost the entire browser is open source,
but if you want to watch a Netflix movie for.
example, then you you need to run this the CDM in addition to just the browser code.
I think we've kind of covered a lot.
I wonder if there's any other examples.
or anything else you thought would be important to mention in in the context of the W3C.
There's one thing which relates to activities I'm doing also at W3C.
Yeah, we've been talking a lot about standards and implementations in browsers,
but there's also adoption of these technology standards by developers in general.
and making sure that developers are aware of what exists, making sure that they understand what exists.
And one of the key pain points.
that people keep raising on the web platform is first the web platform is unique in the sense.
that there are different implementations.
I mean if you anyway there are different context different run times.
where there's just one provided by the company that owns the system.
The web platform is implemented by different organizations.
What's in the specs is not necessarily supported.
And of course MDN tries to document what's supported thoroughly.
But for MDN to work there's a lot of needs for data that tracks browser support.
And this data is typically in a project called the BOZA compat data BCD owned by uh MDN.
as well.
But the open web docs collective is the one maintaining that data under the hood.
Anyway, all of that to say that to make sure.
that we track things beyond work on technical specifications.
because if you look at it from the BC perspective, life ends when the spec reaches standard.
uh you know candidate break or rack.
You could just say, I'm done with my work.
But that's not how things work.
There's always you need the feedback.
And in order to make sure that developers get the information.
and can provide the the feedback that standardization can benefit from.
and browser vendors can benefit from we've been working on a project called web features with browser vendors. mainly.
and a few other folks and MDN.
and can I use and different different people to catalog the web in terms of features.
that speak to developers.
and from that catalog so it's a set of it's a set of feature ids with a feature. name.
and feature description that say you know well this is how developers would uh understand.
instead of going too fine grained in terms of there's this one function call that does this.
because that's where you the the kind of support data you may get from browser compat data. and MDN initially.
and having some kind of coarser grained structure.
that says these are the features that make sense they talk to developers that's what developers talk about.
so we need to have data on these particular features.
because that's how developers are going to approach the space.
and from that we've derived the notion of baseline badges that you have are now.
shown on MDN on can I use and integrated in IDE tools such as Visual Studio.
and libraries some llinters have started to integrate that data.
so the way it works is uh we've been mapping these coarser grained features to BCD's final grained.
support data.
and from there we've been deriving a kind of a batch that says this feature is implemented well.
has limited availability because it's only implemented in one or two browsers for example.
it's newly available because it's implemented across the main browser vendor across the main browsers.
that people use but it's recent.
and widely available which we try to uh.
well there's lots of discussion in the in the group to come up with a definition.
which essentially ends up being 30 months after a feature became newly available.
and that's when that's the time it takes for the versions of the the different versions of the. browsers to propagate.
because you it's not because there's a new version of a of a browser.
that people just im immediately get it.
So it takes a while to propagate across the user user base.
And so the the goal is to have a signal.
that developers can rely on saying okay well it's widely available so I can really use that feature.
And of course if that doesn't work then we need to know about it.
And so we're also working with people doing developer surveys such as state of CSS state of HTML. state of JavaScript.
That's I guess the main ones.
But also we are also running MDN short surveys with MDN people to gather feedback on on these. same features.
and to feed the loop and to complete the loop.
and this data is also used by internally by browser vendors to inform prioritization process their prioritization process.
and typically as part of the interrupt project that they're also running on the stack.
a number of different I've mentioned I guess a number of different projects coming along together.
But that's the goal is to create links across all of these ongoing projects with a view to.
integrating developers more and gathering feedback as early as possible.
and inform decisions we take at the standardization level that can affect the the lives of the developers.
and making sure that it's uh it affects them in a in a positive way.
just trying to understand because you had mentioned that there's the web features and the baseline.
and I was I was trying to picture where developers would actually see these things.
and it sounds like from what you're saying is W3C comes up with what stage some of these. features are at.
and then developers would end up seeing it on MDN or or some other site.
I'm working on it but that doesn't mean it's a W3C thing.
We have different types of group. It's a community group.
So it's the WebDX community group at W3C which means it's a communityowned thing.
So that's why I was mentioning I'm working with representative from the the browser vendors.
and uh people from MDN, people from open web docs and a few of those again. So that's the first point.
The second point is so it's indeed this data is now being integrated if and.
you look you you'll see it on top of the MDN pages on most of them.
If you look at any kind of feature, you'll see a few logos, a baseline banner,
and on can I use it's the same thing.
You're going to get a baseline banner.
It's smaller on can I use and it's meant to capture the fact.
that the feature is widely available or if you may need to pay attention to it.
Of course, it's a simplification.
and the goal is not to the way it's the way the messaging is done to developers is.
meant to capture the fact that.
they may want to look into more than just this baseline status.
Because if you take a look at web platform tests for example.
and if you were to base your assessment of whether a feature is supported based on test results.
you will end up saying the web platform has no supported technology.
because there are absolutely no API that where browsers pass 100% of the test suite.
There may be a few of them. I don't know.
But there's a simplification in the in the process when a feature is said to be baseline.
There may be more things to look at nevertheless.
But it's meant to provide a signal.
that still developers can rely on their day-to-day lives if they use the the feature,
let's say, as reasonably intended.
and not uh using too advanced logic.
I see. Yeah.
I'm looking at one of the pages on MDN right now.
and I can see at the top there's the the baseline.
and it it mentions that this feature works across many browsers and devices.
and then they say how long it's been available.
and so that's a way that people at a glance can can tell which APIs they can use.
It also started out of a desire to summarize this browser compatibility table that you.
see at the end of the page of the the bottom of the page in on MDN.
but there where developers were saying well it's it's fine.
but it's it goes too much into detail so.
we don't know in the end can we use.
that feature or can we can we not use that feature.
so it's meant as a informed summary of of of that it relies on the same data again.
and more importantly we're beyond MDN we're working with tools providers to integrate that as well.
So I mentioned uh Visual Studio is one of them.
So recently they shipped a new version where when you use a feature you can you.
can have some contextual menu that tells you.
yeah that's fine you this CSS property you can use it it's widely available.
or beware this one is limited availability only available in Firefox or or Chrome or Safari or Workit.
I think that's a good place to wrap it up.
If people want to learn more about the work you're doing.
or learn more about sort of this whole recommendations process, where where should they head?
Generally speaking, we're extremely open to people contributing to W3C.
and where should they go if they it depends on what they want to.
So usually where how things start for someone getting involved in W3 Free Siege is.
that they have some kind of a technology in mind.
They have some kind of pet project something that they care about.
and so they find the right GitHub repository in this case probably.
and they start a discussion with people who are actually developing the spec and it may be feedback.
It may be negative feedback, but it may be, hey, I had this ID.
There are different places where you can raise IDs.
So, I don't know where to point at a single place, I guess.
I mean, there's probably a contact email, but it doesn't make a lot of sense.
And that's usually how things start.
And then when people get involved, some of them will like it and uh it's always a pleasure.
when someone enjoys interacting on standards and we'll find ways to encourage their contributions.
Of course, if they represent companies will come a time.
where the process is going to kick in for patent reasons, for different things and for membership fees.
because again that's how the BBC the budget from the BC comes from membership fees.
and so things will kick in and we'll get to the next level.
But initially it's really about just come find a feature you.
that doesn't work for you where you find something that looks clunky in one of the spec.
If you read the spec, it's a it's not always a f fancy read,
but and report report a bug, not in the implementation, but in the spec.
start or propose a new ID to to the group that develops the specification you like,
and we'll take it from there.
And we're very happy to have that feedback.
So maybe find the if there is an existing specification,
go find the the GitHub repository where that's located.
If you have something that you want implemented newly,
maybe find the working group that would be related and start from there.
Absolutely. Franuis, thank you so much for chatting with me today.
I think we we covered a lot about the W3C.
and and how it relates to all the things that we use in our browsers every day. So, thank you.
Thanks a lot for the invitation. Again, been a pleasure.
This has been Jeremy Jung for Software Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by it e software magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.